Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Marketing Vertical Files, 1946-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Marketing Vertical Files 1946-1999
J. Walter Thompson Company.
36 linear feet Extent: 21,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00727
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Marketing Vertical Files were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2000.
Historical Note
Company founded in NY in 1864. The archives document the history, operations, policies, and accomplishments of one of the world's oldest, largest and most innovative advertising firms. These files came from the New York Office's Information Center.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of subject files on a wide range of marketing topics used as reference by J. Walter Thompson Company staff. These topics range from financial information, legal perspectives, employment trends, awards, particular individuals in the industry, media, packaging, trademarks and research; all materials which further reflect the background work and research carried out by J. Walter Thompson Company in the usual course of business. Formats included are primarily newspaper clippings, articles, and pamphlets. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Subject Headings
J. Walter Thompson Company; Advertising -- Research; Advertising laws; Marketing research -- United States; Trademarks; Packaging; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2000-0182
  - General Series
    - Marketing (general) 1965-1995, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - Dictionaries, Terms, 1960-1981 (Box 1)
      - Pamphlets 1955-1975, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Marketing Series (Box 2)
    - Ambush1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Awards 1975-1982 (Box 2)
    - Brands, 1970-1985, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Brands - Brand Equity, 1990-1998, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Brands - Brand Equity, 1990-1998, (1 folder) (Box 3)
    - Brands - Management, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Branding, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Brands - Pamphlets, 1967-1980, (1 of 3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Brands - Pamphlets, 1967-1980, (2 of 3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Brands - Cause-Related, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Brands - Clear-Color, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Brands - Manufacturer vs. Distributor, 1980-1994, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Brands - Manufacturer vs. Distributor - Grocery - Surveys, 1954-1960 (Box 4)
    - Brands - Mature, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Channels, 1975-1986 (Box 4)
    - Event Marketing, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Generational, 1995 (Box 4)
    - History, 1946-1983 (Box 4)
    - Industrial, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Ingredient Branding, 1992-1998 (Box 4)
    - International, 1985-1995 (Box 5)
    - International - Pamphlets, 1962-1973, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Integrated Services, 1990-1993, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Management, 1958-1987, (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Management, 1958-1987, (1 folder) (Box 6)
    - Management - Managers, 1961-1986, (1 folder) (Box 6)
    - Management - Managers, 1961-1986, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Management - Pamphlets, 1953-1969 (Box 6)
    - Management - Planning, 1954-1988, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Management - Planning - Pamphlets, 1956-1985 (Box 7)
    - Management - Specific Companies, 1956-1989 (Box 7)
    - Merchandising - Displays - Window (Box 7)
    - Merchandising - Tags (Box 7)
    - Merchandising - Trade-ins (Box 7)
    - Merchandising - Warranties (Box 7)
    - Merchandising - Warranties - Pamphlets (Box 7)
    - New Products (Box 8)
    - New Products - Line extension (Box 8)
    - New Products - Planning, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - New Products - Introduction (Box 9)
    - New Products - Newsletters (Box 9)
    - New Products - Bibliography (Box 9)
    - New Products - Specific Companies (Box 9)
    - New Products - Planning - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - New Products - Grocery, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - New Products - Planning - Checklists (Box 10)
    - New Products - Planning - Design (Box 10)
    - New Products - Planning - Failures (Box 10)
    - Niche (Box 10)
    - Positioning (Box 10)
    - Price (Box 11)
    - Price - Cutting (Box 11)
    - Price - Discrimination (Box 11)
    - Price - Making, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Price - Making - Administered (Box 11)
    - Price - Maintenance (Box 11)
    - Product Reformulation (Box 11)
    - Regional (Box 12)
    - Relationship Marketing (Box 12)
    - Research, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Research - Pamphlets (Box 12)
    - Research - Bibliography (Box 12)
    - Research - Criticism (Box 12)
    - Research - Data Processing (Box 12)
    - Research - Evaluation (Box 12)
    - Research - International (Box 13)
    - Research - Management (Box 13)
    - Research - Management - Pamphlets (Box 13)
    - Research - Types - Product testing (Box 13)
    - Research - Nation's top (#) marketing/advertising research cos. (Box 13)
    - Research - Techniques, 1963-1983 (Box 13)
    - Research - Techniques - Consumer Panel, 1960-1978 (Box 13)
    - Research - Techniques - Consumer Panel - Pamphlets (Box 14)
    - Research - Techniques - Demometrics, 1985-1986 (Box 14)
    - Research - Techniques - Interview, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Research - Techniques - Interview, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Research - Techniques - Mail Survey (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Motivational (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Motivational -Pamphlets (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Psychographics (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Psychographics - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Questionnaire (Box 15)
    - Research - Techniques - Sample (Box 16)
    - Research - Techniques - Sample - Probability (Box 16)
    - Research - Types (Box 16)
    - Research - Types - Consumer, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Research - Types - Consumer - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Research - Types - Market Analysis (Box 17)
    - Research - Types - Market Analysis - Sales Forecasting, (1 folder, 1 book) (Box 17)
    - Research - Types - Market Analysis - Sales Quota (Box 17)
    - Research - Types - Market Testing - Test cities (Box 17)
    - Research - Types - Motivation (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Pamphlets (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Bibliography (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Consumer (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Consumer - Pamphlets (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Criticism (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Criticism - Pamphlets (Box 18)
    - Research - Types - Motivation - Non-Consumer (Box 18)
    - Retail, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Retail, (2 folders, 1 book) (Box 19)
    - Retail - Pamphlets (Box 19)
    - Retail - Statistics (Box 19)
    - Retail - Statistics (Box 20)
    - Retail - Statistics - Monthly retail trade (Box 20)
    - Retail - Statistics - Retail trade annual report (Box 20)
    - Retail - Weiss, E. B., articles (Box 20)
    - Retail - Appliance and electronic (Box 20)
    - Retail - Appliance and electronic, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Retail - Automated check-out systems, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Retail - Automotive, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Retail - Automotive - Pamphlets (Box 22)
    - Retail - Bookstores, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Retail - Combination stores (Box 22)
    - Retail - Department stores (Box 22)
    - Retail - Department stores - Statistics - Top 25 retailers in general merch. (Box 22)
    - Retail - Department stores - Statistics, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - Retail - Department. stores - Specialty (Box 22)
    - Retail - Discount houses, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Census of discount stores, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Catalog (Box 23)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Leading discount store chains ($100 million club) (Box 23)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Pamphlets (Box 24)
    - Retail - Discount houses - True look of the discount industry (Box 24)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Specific companies, (3 folders) (Box 24)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Specific companies - Sears (Box 24)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Specific companies - K-mart (Box 25)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Specific companies - Wal-Mart (Box 25)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Specific companies - Zayre (Box 25)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Food and Drug (Box 25)
    - Retail - Discount houses - Drug (Box 25)
    - Retail - Drug - Statistics - Lilly Digest, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Retail - Drug - Statistics - Nielsen Review of retail drugstore trends (Box 25)
    - Retail - Drug - Statistics - Sales (Box 25)
    - Retail - Drug - Statistics - Sales - Drug topics annual consumer spending report (Box 26)
    - Retail - Drug - Chains, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - Retail - Drug - Prescriptions (Box 26)
    - Retail - Franchise, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - Retail - Franchise - Franchising in the economy, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Retail - Furniture, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Retail - Gift (Box 27)
    - Retail - Grocery (Box 27)
    - Retail - Grocery - Pamphlets, (3 folders) (Box 27)
    - Retail - Grocery - Pamphlets, ( 1 company folder) (Box 28)
    - Retail - Grocery - Chains - Specific Companies, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Retail - Grocery - Convenience Stores - Specific Companies (Box 28)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics, (3 of 4 folders) (Box 28)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics, (1 of 4 folders) (Box 29)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics - Market Profiles (Box 29)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics - Nielsen Report (Box 29)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics - Sales, (5 folders) (Box 29)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics - Sales, (5 folders) (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Statistics - Sales - Distribution of Food Store Sales (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Chains (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Chains - Location (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Chains - Statistics (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Convenience Stores, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Convenience Stores - CSN Industry Report (Box 30)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets, ( 4 folders) (Box 31)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets, (2 of 4 folders) (Box 31)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Maps (Box 31)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Non-Food, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Non-Food - Health and Beauty, (3 folders) (Box 32)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 32)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Statistics (Box 32)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Statistics - Facts (Box 33)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Statistics - Food Marketing (Box 33)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Statistics -Pamphlets, (3 folders) (Box 33)
    - Retail - Grocery - Supermarkets - Unit Pricing, (2 folders) (Box 33)
    - Retail - Hypermarkets (Box 33)
    - Retail - Jewelry (Box 33)
    - Retail - Non-Store, (2 folders) (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Door-to-Door (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Mail Order (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Mail Order - U.S. Mail Order (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Mail Order - Clubs (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Electronic, (3 folders) (Box 34)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines (Box 35)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines - Statistics (Box 35)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines - Statistics - Vend Census, (2 folders) (Box 35)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines - Food (Box 35)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines - Food - Beverages (Box 35)
    - Retail - Non-Store - Vending Machines - Food Service (Box 35)
    - Retail - Professional Services (Box 35)
    - Retail - Service Stations, (2 folders) (Box 35)
    - Retail - Service Stations - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 36)
    - Retail - Shopping Centers, (2 folders) (Box 36)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits (Box 36)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Pamphlets (Box 36)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Brand Loyalty, (5 folders) (Box 36)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Brand Loyalty, (4 folders) (Box 37)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Buying Decisions, (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Buying Decisions - Pamphlets (Box 37)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Age and Sex, (2 folders) (Box 38)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet (Box 38)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Department Store (Box 38)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Drug, (2 folders) (Box 38)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Grocery, (2 folders) (Box 38)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Grocery (Box 39)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Grocery - Burgoyne Survey (Box 39)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Grocery - Pamphlets, Pamphlets (6 of 7 folders) (Box 39)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Outlet - Grocery - Pamphlets (Box 40)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - By Time and Location (Box 40)
    - Retail - Shopping Habits - Impulse Buying (Box 40)
    - Retail - Sporting Goods (Box 40)
    - Retail - Store Hours (Box 40)
    - Retail - Superstores (Box 40)
    - Retail - Toy and Hobby (Box 40)
    - Retail - Variety Stores (Box 40)
    - Retail - Variety Stores - Specific Companies, (2 folders) (Box 40)
    - Retail - Variety Stores - Self-Service (Box 41)
    - Retail - Variety Stores - Statistics (Box 41)
    - Retail - Warehouse Clubs (Box 41)
    - Sales Management (Box 41)
    - Sales Management - Pamphlets (Box 41)
    - Sales Management - Survey of Selling Costs, (2 folders) (Box 41)
    - Sales Management - Meetings, (2 folders) (Box 42)
    - Sales Management - Sales Aids (Box 42)
    - Sales Management - Sales Aids - Advertising (Box 42)
    - Sales Management - Sales Managers, (2 folders) (Box 42)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen, (3 folders) (Box 42)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - As an Occupation (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Auto Allowances (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Compensation (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Costs (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Incentives, (3 folders) (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Incentives - Sales and Marketing Management (Box 43)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Training, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Selling, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Management - Salesmen - Selling - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Promotions, (4 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Promotions, (3 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Promotions - Pamphlets, (3 folders) (Box 44)
    - Sales Promotions - Advertising Age (Box 45)
    - Sales Promotions - Arts (Box 45)
    - Sales Promotions - Conventions, Exhibits and Shows, (2 folders) (Box 45)
    - Sales Promotions - Managers (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Advertising Age (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Contests, (2 folders) (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Coupons, (2 of 3 folders) (Box 46)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Coupons, (1 of 3 folders) (Box 47)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Coupons - Pamphlets (Box 47)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Coupons - Redemption (Box 47)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Premiums, (5 folders) (Box 47)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Premiums - Pamphlets (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Premiums - Annual Industry Report (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Premiums - Rebates (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Premiums - Selecting (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Promotion Index (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Sampling, (2 folders) (Box 48)
    - Sales Promotions - Offers - Top promos (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - School (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - Special Days and Weeks, (2 folders) (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - Special Events (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - Sports (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - Sports - Olympics, (4 folders) (Box 49)
    - Sales Promotions - Sports, (3 folders) (Box 49)
    - Trading Stamps, (2 folders) (Box 50)
    - Trading Stamps - Statistics (Box 50)
    - Trading Stamps - Surveys (Box 50)
    - Trading Stamps - Grocery (Box 50)
    - Trading Stamps - Criticism (Box 50)
    - Trading Stamps - Stamp companies (Box 50)
    - Value Added by Distribution (Box 50)
    - Warehouses (Box 50)
    - Wholesale (Box 50)
    - Wholesale - Pamphlets (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Agents, brokers and resident buyers (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Agents, brokers and resident buyers - Food brokers (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Distributors (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Drug (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Grocery (Box 51)
    - Wholesale - Jobbers (Box 52)
  - Markets Series
    - Consumer, (3 folders) (Box 52)
    - Consumer - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 52)
    - Consumer - Pamphlets, (4 folders) (Box 53)
    - Consumer - By Age, (3 folders) (Box 53)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth, (2 folders) (Box 53)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Pamphlets, (4 folders) (Box 54)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Children, (2 folders) (Box 54)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Teenage, (2 folders) (Box 54)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Teenage - Pamphlets (Box 54)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Teenage - Pamphlets, (3 folders) (Box 55)
    - Consumer - By Age - Youth - Current Population Reports, (2 folders) (Box 55)
    - Consumer - By Income, (2 folders) (Box 55)
    - Consumer - By Sex - Women - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 55)
    - Consumer - By Sex - Women - Pamphlets, (2 folders) (Box 56)
    - Consumer - By Sex - Women - Brides, (2 folders) (Box 56)
    - Consumer - By Sex - Women - Brides - Pamphlets, (4 folders) (Box 56)
    - Consumer - By Social Class (Box 57)
    - Consumer - Consumer Protection, (3 folders) (Box 57)
    - Consumer - Consumer Protection - Pamphlets, (4 of 7 folders) (Box 57)
    - Consumer - Consumer Protection - Pamphlets, (3 of 7 folders) (Box 58)
    - Consumer - Ethnic, (2 folders) (Box 58)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black, (3 folders) (Box 58)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black, (folder 4 of 4) (Box 59)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black - Pamphlets, (4 folders) (Box 59)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black - The Gibson Report, (2 folders) (Box 59)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black - The Gibson Report, (folder 3 of 3) (Box 60)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Black - Social and Economic Status, (3 folders) (Box 60)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Spanish, (2 folders) (Box 60)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Spanish - Pamphlets, (2 of 6 folders) (Box 60)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Spanish - Pamphlets, (4 of 6 folders) (Box 61)
    - Consumer - Ethnic - Spanish - Persons of Spanish Origin in the U.S., . (2 folders) (Box 61)
    - Industrial (Box 61)
    - Industrial - Survey, (2 folders) (Box 62)
    - Institutional (Box 62)
    - Special markets - Blacks, 1985 (Box 62)
    - Special markets - Men, undated (Box 62)
  - Oversize Materials
    - Marketing - Retail - Grocery - Statistics (Box 63)
    - Marketing - Retail - Discount Houses - Pamphlets (Box 63)